בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ד. chaf dalet. We
pick up in the middle of the עמוד amud right before the
משנה. mishnah. We were dealing with the issue
about that a slave is, can be a שליח. shaliach. The requirement,
there's two basic requirements of being a שליח. shaliach. One is that
you have to be part of the Jewish community and the גמרא
gemara was trying to figure out what, from the פסוק pasuk of
גם אתם gam atem by תרומה, terumah, what the boundary of that
is. It would exclude a non-Jew, but the question is would it
also exclude a slave because they're not considered ישראל? Yisrael? But the
גמרא gemara concludes that actually a slave would be included because they
would be considered a בן ברית, ben brit, obligated in the מצוות.
mitzvot. רש"י Rashi refers to the פסוק pasuk by at the end
of דברים Dvarim about חוטב עציך, chotzev etzecha, considered to be in
the ברית. brit. So therefore they're not categorically excluded. But nevertheless there's
another requirement that to be a שליח shaliach for a particular area
you need to be a, what's often called like a בר הכי.
bar hachi. So like the laws have to be relevant to you.
So a slave could be a שליח shaliach for תרומות ומעשרות terumot
u'maasrot because those laws are relevant. But a slave cannot be a
שליח shaliach for גיטין וקידושין gittin ve'kiddushin because there's no binding קידושין
kiddushin and גיטין gittin that applies to a slave even though a
slave is חייב chayav in מצוות. mitzvot. So that's why a slave
cannot be a שליח shaliach for those purposes. So that's basically what
we concluded yesterday. And now the גמרא gemara ends, ended a statement
and we sort of left the second half of a statement to
dangle. So before the משנה mishnah we have the following. It says,
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, line start
with the word אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan about fifteen lines
from the top. אין עבד נעשה שליח לקבל גט אשה מיד בעלה,
ein eved na'aseh shaliach l'kabel get isha miyad ba'alah, a slave cannot
be a שליח shaliach to accept a bill of divorce. You can
put a bill of divorce in a, on a slave owned by
the woman because that's like on her property, but another person's slave
cannot be a שליח shaliach for that. לפי שאינו בתורת גיטין וקידושין,
lefi she'eino b'torat gittin ve'kiddushin, because he's not in the Torah, in
the category of גיטין gittin and קידושין. kiddushin. ואף על פי ששנינו,
ve'af al pi she'shaninu, although we taught, הרי את שפחה וולדך בן
חורין, harey at shifchah u'vladach ben chorin, that a person can give
to his female slave a writ of freedom, a שטר שחרור, shtar
shichrur, and say you remain a slave but your unborn child that
you are currently carrying I am freeing your unborn child by giving
you this, by giving him or her or whatever this bill of
freedom, this גט שחרור get shichrur that you are accepting on behalf
of your unborn child. That that actually works. אם היתה עוברה זכתה
לו. im hayta ubarah zachsa lo. So if basically she was pregnant
with this child, she takes possession of this writ of manumission for
the child and the child is freed.
If she's not a שליח shaliach for עובר, ubar, what does it
mean?
Well, that's the גמרא'ס gemara's point. So let's take a look. מאי
mai אם היתה עוברה זכתה לו? im hayta ubarah zachsa lo? So
how is that relevant to the discussion about whether a slave can
be a שליח? shaliach? Because anyway as Dov said, so how is
she functioning here? Is she functioning as a שליח shaliach for her
fetus? And number one, number two is this would not be a
problem that he's not בתורת גיטין וקידושין. b'torat gittin ve'kiddushin. A slave
is certainly בתורת שחרור b'torat shichrur in a category that he could
receive a, or she could receive a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for
him or herself. So there should, why should that be a, why
is this even though we said, this is still not a problem,
this isn't a challenge to the idea? Why should it be a
challenge to the idea? Just because you can't be a שליח shaliach
for גיטין וקידושין, gittin ve'kiddushin, no reason you shouldn't be able to
be a שליח shaliach for, you know, to accept a גט שחרור
get shichrur for another slave. You're in the category of שטר שחרור.
shtar shichrur. So the גמרא gemara says, so why is this a
challenge? What's the issue here? כי אתא רב שמואל בר יהודה אמר
רבי יוחנן תרתי אמר. ki ata Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda amar Rabbi
Yochanan tarti amar. No, you're right. He said two things, they really
weren't related. Because this is not related to the idea that you
can't be a שליח shaliach for גט, get, a slave can't be
a שליח shaliach for גט, get, because he's not in the category
of גט. get. This is really, this אף על פי שאמרו af
al pi she'amru is really coming to qualify or to clarify a
different point that was made. What was the different point that was
made? מילי דהכי שעבד מקבל גט לחבירו מיד רבו של חבירו, miley
d'hachi she'eved mekabel get l'chavero miyad rabo she'chavero, that it was a,
that that was the transition. You a slave cannot accept a
גט get or be a שליח shaliach for גיטין וקידושין gittin ve'kiddushin
because he's not in that category of גט. get. But a slave
could be a שליח shaliach to accept a writ of manumission, a
שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for a fellow slave, because a slave is
in the category of שחרור. shichrur. So that's okay. So I can
accept a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for my friend from my friend's
master, from my friend's owner. אבל לא מיד רבו שלו. aval lo
miyad rabo shelo. If
however let's say my master owns me and another slave. He can't
give me a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur to accept it on behalf
of this other slave that he owns. Why not? Why can't I
be a שליח? shaliach? Sometimes you can be a שליח. shaliach. But
the problem is is that the master has to give it to
someone else. And since then... he's giving, he's your master and he's
giving it to you, it's like he's putting it in his own
hand, right? It's not like he's putting it, now you could say
when he frees his own when if he were to free you,
he would put it in his own hand. But there you can
and that's a Gemara גמרא Gemara question the Gemara גמרא Gemara asks
also by a get of an isha גט של אשה get shel
isha that why don't we say kanat isha kanat ba'alah קנתה אשה
קנה בעלה, kanat isha kanat ba'alah, how does she possess it for
herself? So here the point the principle there is gitov veyado ba'im
ke'echad גיטו וידו באים כאחד. gitov veyado ba'im ke'echad. That since in
this act of giving the get גט, get, you become a free
man, or when I give a get גט get to my wife,
she becomes divorced and is able to take possession property on her
own, then in that same act that that is effecting that, she's
like sort of at all the same time she achieves the right
and that independence to take possession for herself. Or for the take
a slave that's considered to be I'm not just handing it from
my right hand to my left hand, I'm giving it into a
different domain because this act is actually acknowledging and creating the slave
as a free person. That's when I free the slave in that
act. But when I'm not freeing the slave in the act, I'm
giving it to slave one to take possession of it for slave
two, it's like I took it from my right hand and I
put it into my left hand, and that's not an act of
giving a shtar shichrur שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, and that doesn't work.
So even though he could be a shaliach שליח, shaliach, right, he
cannot actually represent himself as some different domain, different entity, in order
that it be considered a legitimate act of netinah נתינה. netinah. They
tell a joke or there's more of a Kiddushin קידושין Kiddushin joke,
but whatever, they tell a joke that a rabbi goes into a
yeshiva ישיבה yeshiva and says what are you all learning so we're
learning Masechet Kiddushin מסכת קידושין. Masechet Kiddushin. So he says, "Okay," he
says, "can a," you know, "can an androgynous אנדרוגינוס androgynous be mekadesh
מקדש mekadesh himself?" So the student says, "Well, I don't know, it's
in an act of netinah נתינה netinah because who are you giving
it to another person? You're just giving it to yourself, going back
and forth." And he says, "Of course not, he's his sister." But
anyway,
okay.
All right, so anyway, so you can't, even though he can be
a shaliach שליח shaliach to accept a bill of freedom, a shtar
shichrur שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for, from another master, he cannot accept
a shtar shichrur שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for a fellow slave from
his own master. Yad rabo shelo יד רבו שלו yad rabo shelo
considered as hand of the rav רב. rav. What? The rav רב
rav hasn't given
it, it's not a ma'aseh netinah מעשה נתינה, ma'aseh netinah, it's like
giving the rav רב rav gave it from his right hand to
his left hand, because this slave even after accepting this shtar שטר
shtar remains possession of the rav רב. rav.
Right, and unless gitov veyado ba'im ke'echad גיטו וידו באים כאחד gitov
veyado ba'im ke'echad is only if it's by yourself.
Exactly, only if you're becoming free in that act. Ve'im lachashcha adam
lomar ואם לחשך אדם לומר, ve'im lachashcha adam lomar, if a person
whispers to you, you gotta love that phrase, and says, "Oh, how
can you say such a thing? Zu halacha shenuyah זו הלכה שנויה,
zu halacha shenuyah, how could you say that you can't give it
to one slave to free another if they're both your slaves? But
don't we have, haven't we taught im hayetah ubarah zachah lo אם
הייתה עוברה זכה לו, im hayetah ubarah zachah lo, if a slave
woman was pregnant, I can give it to my slave woman and
it frees the fetus? So there she's taking possession, they're both my
slaves and one is taking possession of a shtar shichrur שטר שחרור
shtar shichrur for the other. Where's the ma'aseh netinah מעשה נתינה ma'aseh
netinah there?" So emor lo אמור לו, emor lo, say back to
that person, shenei gedolei hador perishu et hadavar שני גדולי הדור פירשו
את הדבר, shenei gedolei hador perishu et hadavar, two of the greats
of the generation interpreted this, u-manu ומנו, u-manu, and who are Rabbi
Zeira ve-Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak רבי זירא ורבי שמואל בר רב
יצחק. Rabbi Zeira ve-Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak. Chad amar חד אמר,
chad amar, and they basically gave like two sort of complementary explanations.
Ha mni Rabbi hi הא מני רבי היא. ha mni Rabbi hi.
No no, that is based on the teaching of Rabbi רבי, Rabbi,
de-amar hamishacher chetzi avdo kanah דאמר המשחרר חצי עבדו קנה. de-amar hamishacher
chetzi avdo kanah. I can free half my slave. So we would
say gitov veyado ba'im ke'echad גיטו וידו באים כאחד gitov veyado ba'im
ke'echad even if he didn't become a complete independent entity. Okay, not
exactly how do you free half and which half or whatever, but
I am like renouncing my ownership over half of you, I am
freeing half of you. So Rabbi רבי Rabbi says that actually works
and because enough, half of him is freeing, he can take possession
of the shtar shichrur שטר שחרור shtar shichrur for that half that's
being freed. Okay, and now add to that the following idea. Vechad
amar וחד אמר, vechad amar, the other says, it's a different explanation
but it's a complementary one. Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi beha מאי טעמא דרבי
בהא, mai ta'ama de-Rabbi beha, and how would Rabbi's רבי Rabbi idea
apply in this case here about the pregnant slave? Ubar yerech imo
hu עובר ירך אמו הוא, ubar yerech imo hu, the fetus is
not considered a separate entity but considered part of the mother. Denafek
minei she'it lei leachad me'eivarav דנפק מיני שית ליה לאחד מאיבריו. denafek
minei she'it lei leachad me'eivarav. So it's like I said I'm freeing
your leg, your leg now doesn't doesn't isn't owned to me anymore,
your arm isn't owned to me. I can't ask for you to
do any work with your right arm, your right arm is yours.
Okay, I only get work out of your left arm. Okay, so
that's an interesting idea of chetzi eved חצי עבד, chetzi eved, an
actual very identifiable part of the slave you're freeing. Okay, but if
we say that, then she is, it's a type of gitov veyado
ba'im ke'echad גיטו וידו באים כאחד gitov veyado ba'im ke'echad because since
in this taking of it, part of her becomes her own entity,
even though it's not the fetus that is taking possession of the
of the, you know, physically, if it's a physical thing, that it's
the get גט get is in her hand, it's not in the
fetus's hand, but that idea that conceptually since this act this act
is coming with some of her own freedom attached to it, then
therefore that conceptually creates enough of a separate entity that she can
actually take possession, which is definitely a chiddush חידוש. chiddush. Okay, so
that's the principle. So a slave can be a shaliach שליח shaliach
for something that is relevant to him or her, so for Terumot
and Ma'asrot תרומות ומעשרות Terumot and Ma'asrot yes, for shtar shichrur שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur yes, not for get גט get and Kiddushin קידושין,
Kiddushin, but you can't give a shtar shichrur שטר שחרור shtar shichrur
to one slave to. get work for another slave of yours because
then there's no act of giving, it's all staying within your direct
control. Except you can free your own slave and you can even
free half of your slave or the fetus of a slave and
that would all work, yes.
Is this conceptually similar to שפחה חרופה? Shifchah Charufah?
Well שפחה חרופה Shifchah Charufah is the case of a half-freed slave.
Half and half, right?
Yes, so that's the... yes. So yes, it is a similar case.
Yeah, in the case of מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin and there's מחלוקת
machloket between בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, חכמים
Chachamim also...
well, whether you allow that status to remain. But yes. Okay, so
now we continue. Yeah.
So when we had the example the other day of the tree
with the stone in between. Right. And we were discussing with
the stone in between, things go from one side to the other.
It's something about this thing about freeing half of a slave that
disconnects totally the person from the parts of the body or something.
Right. Right. No, you're right, it is very similar. And then the
fact, I mean, a normal half of a slave is just conceptually
you're half free, right? Not a particular part of your body. And
then we're actually making it, you're right, sort of like that rock
that goes between the tree, to actually identify a specific part of
the body.
Exactly. How do you define half slave?
Exactly. No, so if you just say a half, it's not any
particular part of the body. And then what's the halachic status of
somebody that's half free? I mean, how you know... that's like I
understand. So that's like a lot of, so, so particularly there's one
אחרון, Acharon, the חינוך, Chinuch, who he loves exploring that question. What's
the halachic status of somebody that's half free? But that's the entirety
of him. It's like, you know, as opposed to a particular piece
of the body which is in this case. Alright.
So if the master says, 'Make me a cup of coffee,' and
he does it with his right hand.
Right, exactly. Exactly. Okay. Okay, let's take a look at the next
משנה. Mishnah. אף הנשים שאינם נאמנות לומר מת בעלה, Af hanashim she'einam
ne'emanot lomar met ba'alah,
so we mentioned who can write a גט, Get, who can bring
a גט. Get. And now that we're mentioning who can bring a
גט Get and who might be disqualified because they're not a בר
דעת bar da'at or not a בר שליחות bar shlichut or whatever,
we're going to talk about people that might not be able to
bring a גט Get because they have to say בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם Bifnei nichtav u'vifnei nechtam or because maybe they're just anyway חשוד
chashud of trying to make ruin this woman's life and maybe it's
a forgery and maybe we have to be concerned. So that's what
the משנה Mishnah says, we actually are not concerned about that. אף
הנשים שאינם נאמנות לומר מת בעלה, Af hanashim she'einam ne'emanot lomar met
ba'alah,
women who are not believed to tell a husband, another woman over
in מסכת יבמות Masechet Yevamot that her husband died, we believe an
עד אחד, ed echad, we believe a woman, but there are certain
people we don't believe because we're afraid they're giving her false information
and they want her to remarry and then her husband's going to
show up alive and her life is going to be a mess.
So those women that we don't believe because we think they might
have something in for this woman to say that her husband died,
nevertheless נאמנות להביא את גיטה, ne'emanot l'havi et gittah,
they can bring a גט Get and we don't suspect that the
גט Get is forged. Okay, because you got a גט Get with
witnesses signed on it. So who are these women? חמותה, chamotah, the
mother-in-law, ובת חמותה, u'vat chamotah, the mother-in-law's daughter, so the sister-in-law. All
these women we feel, you know, we don't know always, but we
feel sometimes they can have something out for this new woman in
their family.
What a fantastic idea.
וצרתה, v'tzaratah, her co-wife, that's pretty obvious. ויבמתה, v'yevamtah,
her husband's brother's sister. Why? הגמרא HaGemara says her husband's brother's wife.
Her husband's brother's wife. Why? Because if her husband dies and she's
left without children, then her husband's brother will do יבום Yibum with
her and then she'll become a צרה tzarah to the existing wife.
Okay, so that co-wife always is, you know... okay, ויבמתה ובת בעלה,
v'yevamtah u'vat ba'alah, her stepdaughter. Okay, so all these women are, you
know, again, we don't say always, but it's possible that they could
have something against this woman and when they're not believed to say
that her husband died, they're believed to bring a גט. Get. מה
בין גט למיתה? Mah bein Get l'mitah? What's the difference? שהכתב מוכיח,
she'haktav mochiach, because here you have a writ and that is something
that, you know, it's not saying that people can't write a גט
Get but it's signed, right? So it's signed by witnesses. So you're
not suspecting that somebody forged this. האישה עצמה מביאה גיטה, Ha'ishah atzmah
meviah gittah, a woman could bring her own גט. Get. והיא שליח
לעצמה, v'hi shaliach l'atzmah, talk about a מתנה ונתינה, matanah v'netinah, we're
going to discuss that in the גמרא, Gemara, how can she give
it to herself, where's the act of נתינה? netinah? ובלבד שצריכה לומר
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. u'vilvad she'tzrichah lomar bifnei nichtav u'vifnei nechtam. So
she has to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nichtav u'vifnei nechtam
which is pretty funny because if the husband gave it to her,
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nichtav u'vifnei nechtam is only when you're
bringing it from one place to another. So where's she bringing it
to? How does she give it to herself? Where's she bringing it
to? And why is she bringing it from, you know, a distant
place that she has to say בפני נכתב? bifnei nichtav? So we'll
see all that in the גמרא. Gemara. Is it a תנא, Tanna,
right? Well, yeah, but then why would you... we'll see about this
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, ותניא v'tanya says the גמרא, Gemara, כשם
שאינה נאמנת לומר מת בעלה כך אינה נאמנת להביא את גיטה, keshem
she'eina ne'emanet lomar met ba'alah kach eina ne'emanet l'havi et gittah, that
the women who are not believed to
say the husband died
are not believed to bring the גט. Get. And we could say
it's a debate, but maybe there's a way of reconciling these two
teachings. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב יוסף לא קשיא
כאן
בארץ כאן בחוץ
לארץ. Amar Rav Yosef lo kashya kan b'Eretz kan b'Chutz la'Aretz. It
depends, are they bringing it in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where they
don't have to say בפני נכתב, bifnei nichtav, or in חוץ לארץ
Chutz la'Aretz where they do, or from חוץ לארץ. Chutz la'Aretz. בארץ
דלאו אדיבורא דידה סמכינן, B'Eretz d'lav adibura didah samchinan, in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael where they're not testifying to anything. just bringing it. And
the שטר shtar and the גט get is speaking for itself with
its own testimony. So לא, lo, so in that case מהימנת, mehemnat,
she's believed,
because mostly what she's saying is that she's not testifying to the
validity of the גט, get, she's just saying that she's a שליח,
shaliach, and even her status as a שליח shaliach is pretty implicit
from the fact that she's carrying a גט. get. So there's very
little that we're actually relying on her, we're really all relying on
the witnesses. So in that case it's not a problem. בחוץ לארץ
דדיבורא דידה קא סמכינן, B'chutz la'aretz d'dibura dida ka samchinan, in חוץ
לארץ chutz la'aretz where she needs to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם
befani nechtav ubefani nechtam to validate her role as a שליח shaliach
or this thing's validity as a גט, get, in that case לא
מהימנא, lo mehemna, she's not going to be believed because we are
afraid that she could lie about that.
Of course she would still have to forge the גט, get, but
nevertheless, because it's about her testifying, we don't want to believe her
testimony. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, Abaye said, אדרבה, ad
raba, the opposite makes sense, איפכא מסתברא, ipcha mistabra, the opposite is
what makes sense. בארץ, B'aretz, in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, דאתי בעל
מערער משכחינן בה, d'ati ba'al m'ar'er mashkachinan bah, since there's no testimony
of בפני נכתב, befani nechtav, yeah, the woman can get married with
this right away, but if the גט get is ever challenged then
it's by the husband, it's going to be a problem, and she's
going to need to validate, and if she can't validate it, she's
going to be messed up. So she's
really vulnerable to being hurt by this whole thing in the case
that it's in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So דאיכא למימר לכולה קא
מכוונא, d'ika l'meimar l'kula ka michavna, so maybe she's bringing this גט
get to ruin this woman's life. So לא מהימנא, lo mehemna, so
in that case she will not be believed, meaning even though she's
barely saying anything, but we don't accept the גט, get, we are
concerned it might be forged, we don't believe that she's really a
שליח shaliach because it could be that this whole she's doing this
whole thing to set up the woman. Okay. בחוץ לארץ דאתי בעל
מערער לא משכחינן בה, B'chutz la'aretz d'ati ba'al m'ar'er lo mashkachinan bah,
but in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz where the husband if he were
to come and complain, once you said בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, befani
nechtav ubefani nechtam, the גט get cannot be challenged. So in that
case מהימנא, mehemna, she should be believed. Now of course what you
could still do is the witnesses who signed the גט get could
come and say we never signed it. So it's not like it's
completely bulletproof, like completely impervious to any type of attack. Right, but
the point is that that presumably would be the other opinion. One
opinion is saying is I don't want to believe any testimony she
says. Okay, as long as it's not saying testimony I'm fine. The
other one says, I don't want to believe a case, I don't
want to have her delivered in a case where maybe she's setting
even if she's not testifying, she's setting the whole thing up to
ruin this woman, and therefore I adopt the don't want to believe
her in a case of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So I'm just
saying in the case of חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, the one where
it says she's not believed in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, what's he
afraid of? Because if so he's afraid of a scenario presumably it's
true, if the husband were to challenge it, the husband wouldn't be
believed, but presumably he's still afraid of a scenario where the עדים
edim would come and say the whole thing is a forgery and
then her life would be ruined. Okay, so that's the debate.
תניא כוותיה דאביי, Tanya k'vatei d'Abaye, we taught like Abaye, that it
really is that the problem is in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where
she is left really vulnerable. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer mishum Rabbi Akiva, אשה נאמנת להביא
גיטה מקל וחומר. Ishah ne'emenet l'havi gitah mi'kal vachomer. A woman can
bring her own גט get from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה
נשים שאמרו חכמים אין נאמנות לומר מת בעלה נאמנות להביא את גיטה,
Ma nashim she'amru chachamim ein ne'emanot lomar met ba'ala ne'emanot l'havi et
gita, women that are not believed to say that the woman's husband
died can bring the גט, get, היא שנאמנת לומר מת בעלה, hi
she'ne'emenet lomar met ba'ala, a woman who herself who can say that
her husband who is believed to say her husband died in those
discussions in יבמות, Yevamot, אינו דין שנאמנת להביא גיטה, eino din she'ne'emenet
l'havi gita, shouldn't she also be able to bring her own גט?
get? Okay, so ממקום שבאת, mimakom shebata, but if we're making a
קל וחומר kal vachomer that a woman can bring her own גט
get because from the fact that these other women can bring a
גט, get, so then it has to be limited by that initial
case. מה להלן צריכה שתאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, Ma lehalan tzricha
shetomar befani nechtav ubefani nechtam, the same way where these other women
bring a גט, get, they have to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם,
befani nechtav ubefani nechtam, אף היא af hi when she brings her
own גט, get, צריכה שתאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, tzricha shetomar befani
nechtav ubefani nechtam, she has to say it. So that's just establishing
the second part of the משנה mishna that a woman can bring
her own גט, get, but what's implicit is, when are we believing
these other women who bring a גט? get? When they say בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם. befani nechtav ubefani nechtam. So we're believing these other
women when they're bringing the גט get from חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz.
So that shows like Abaye, that when these women bring a גט
get from חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, they're believed because they're actually, as
opposed to when they testify the husband is dead where the woman
is very vulnerable to having her life ruined if the husband shows
up, or as opposed to when they bring the גט get in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where she's vulnerable to having her life ruined
if the husband shows up and says I never wrote the גט,
get, when they bring it from חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz and testify
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, befani nechtav ubefani nechtam, this woman is really
pretty protected and that because she's so protected, there's really very little
to be concerned about. Okay, so then the גמרא gemara says, אמר
רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, מתניתין נמי דיקא, matnitin nami dika, our
משנה mishna also if you read closely supports this idea, דקתני האשה
עצמה מביאה גיטה ובלבד שצריכה לומר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, dekatani ha'isha
atzma mevi'ah gita u'vilvad she'tzricha lomar befani nechtav ubefani nechtam, that it
talks-
says that the woman has to say it, so clearly we're talking
in a scenario of חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, that's the context of
the משנה mishna and that's the context of these other women as
well. שמע מינה. Shma mina. That's a good proof. רב יוסף *Rav
Yosef*, now how about רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* who says that the
women are only believed in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*? רישא וסיפא בחוץ
לארץ, מציעתא בארץ *reisha ve-seifa b'chutz la'aretz, metzi'asa ba-aretz*? How does that
work? The end of the case of the woman bringing her own
גט get *get* is a case of בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam* of
חוץ לארץ *Chutz La'aretz*. The beginning of a משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* that
says that a סומא *suma* cannot bring a גט get *get*, anybody
remember why a סומא *suma* can't bring a גט get *get*? A
blind person?
Because he
can't say בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam* is talking about חוץ לארץ *Chutz
La'aretz*. So we have the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* about סומא *suma* חוץ
לארץ *Chutz La'aretz*, the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* about the woman herself bringing
her own גט get *get* חוץ לארץ *Chutz La'aretz*. This middle case
of these other women, all of a sudden it's talking about ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*?
Sorry, about three different משניות *mishnayot*.
Yeah, okay, but it's all juxtaposed. Right, well, I don't know exactly
where they broke the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, but anyway, but it's all
juxtaposed. These three cases follow one another. The people that are פסול
pasul. *pasul* to bring a גט get *get* is a סומא *suma*
because he can't say בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam*. These women are כשר
kasher *kasher*, a woman herself, the wife herself could bring because she
says בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam*. So the first case is בפני נחתם
*b'fanay nechtam*, the last case is בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam*, the middle
case of these women is not a בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam* case?
That doesn't make any sense. רישא וסיפא בחוץ לארץ, מציעתא בארץ *reisha
ve-seifa b'chutz la'aretz, metzi'asa ba-aretz*? אין *In*, yes, רישא וסיפא בחוץ לארץ,
מציעתא בארץ *reisha ve-seifa b'chutz la'aretz, metzi'asa ba-aretz*. Okay, so that's one
way of answering it. Yeah, fine, that is what it's talking about.
But obviously, the evidence is that the whole context of all of
it is a בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam* context, and that completely supports
אביי Abaye *Abaye* that these women are believed not דוקא *davka* because
they're saying בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam*, they're believed because then this woman
is
really protected against attack.
Yes, I thought it's quite interesting what you just said.
We see the terminology of רישא *reisha* and סיפא *seifa* all over
the place. But how do we know if they broke the משנה
Mishnah *Mishna* at all? Or...
right, I mean I think yeah that's a... I don't know, I
mean there's a scholarly discussion about that about like where the משנה
mishnah *Mishna* is exactly broken and...
yeah,
I mean and to what degree even in the...
it's all decontextualized whenever they say רישא *reisha* and סיפא *seifa* it's
because they're focusing on some piece but maybe it wasn't broken up
the way we think...
well, it certainly was divided into פרקים prakim. *prakim*. I don't know
at what stage it was divided into individual משניות *mishnayot* but even
when it was, it's not like everybody had the same division. I
mean the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* is completely different... so that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is connected, right, so that you help organize it. But you
know, how much is that different than when we're working within a
משנה mishnah. *Mishna* and then the editor takes three words from the
משנה mishnah? *Mishna* and tells you now we're going to be dealing
with this part of the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, you know, and puts
it between those two dots. You could imagine that a whole משנה
Mishnah *Mishna* or a פרק perek, *perek* was all together and everything
was just on this part... it's a problem when people learn ירושלמי
*Yerushalmi* because the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* that they have... when the whole
ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* is based on one manuscript, it's just pretty like amazing.
Like I mean, there were obviously many many manuscripts but we've lost
them all in history. There's only one manuscript that survived. If you
imagine what would have happened if that manuscript hadn't survived. Anyway, so
but the point is that manuscript did not have the משניות *mishnayot*
in it, it just had the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. So when they printed
the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*, they used a separate משנה Mishnah *Mishna* to print
together like you know and they printed it like all at the
beginning sometimes, I think in the original Venice edition they printed the
entire משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* at the beginning and they didn't even break
it up like the entire משנה *Mishna* of a פרק perek *perek*.
But besides which that then often the text of the משנה *Mishna*
that they used was not the text of the משנה *Mishna* that
the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* had. So sometimes you're not understanding what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is talking about because they're actually dealing with a different
משנה *Mishna*. Anyway. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
You're saying they inferred the משנה *Mishna*? What? You're saying they inferred
the משנה *Mishna* from the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*?
No, they just used a standard משנה *Mishna* text and they printed
it together with the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*.
משנה *Mishna* from בבלי *Bavli* then?
What? Yeah or from independent כתבי יד *kisvey yad* of the משנה
*Mishna*. ירושלמי כתבי יד *Yerushalmi kisvey yad*. Okay, anyway, so... okay. מציעתא
בארץ *metzi'asa ba-aretz*. ממאי דקתני *Mimai de-katani* now, what encourages רב יוסף
*Rav Yosef* to have his read that the case about these women
is in ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* since all the good evidence is
that it's חוץ לארץ *Chutz La'aretz*? ממאי דקתני מה בין גט get
למיתה שהכתב מוכיח *Mimai de-katani ma bein get l'misa she-haksav mochiach*. Because
the משנה *Mishna* said the reason we believe them is because of
the writ. Okay, which sounds like it's the גט get *get* doing
its entire testimony, that the woman isn't saying anything. That pushed him
to say that we're believing these women דוקא *davka* in ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael* because we don't have to trust their testimony. I know
that this wife is potentially vulnerable, but he reads the משנה *Mishna*
that the משנה *Mishna* is saying the reason we believe them is
because they're not saying anything, because it's just the גט get *get*.
מפני שהכתב מוכיח *mipnei she-haksav mochiach*. ולא קתני שהכתב והפה מוכיח *v'lo
katani she-haksav v'ha-peh mochiach*. According to you guys that it was talking
in חוץ לארץ *Chutz La'aretz* and it was בפני נחתם *b'fanay nechtam*,
it should have said because the writ backs up what she is
saying. But by just saying it's the writ itself, that to him
says that it sounds like it's talking דוקא *davka* in ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael*. Okay, so we have that debate although all the evidence
is that we're talking in חוץ לארץ *Chutz La'aretz*, she's more believed
because the writ backs up what she's saying and because it's leaving
the woman protected rather than vulnerable. Okay. האשה עצמה מביאה גיטה *ha-isha
atzma mevia gitta*, a woman can bring her own גט get. *get*.
אמר הגמרא *amar ha-Gemara* says, אשה מכדי מטי גיטא לידה איגרשה לה
Lah *isha mikdei mati gitta l'yada igrashah lah*? How does a woman
become a שליח shaliach *shaliach* to deliver a גט get *get* to
herself? As soon as the גט get *get* gets to her hand,
she's divorced. אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna *Amar Rav Huna*, באומר
*b'omer* Abaye says אשה מכיוון דאתי גיטא לידה איגרשה לה how does
a woman become a שליח shaliach, to deliver herself a גט get
to herself? As soon as the גט get, gets to her hand
she's divorced. אמר רב הונא באומר לא תתגרשי בו אלא בפני בית
דין פלוני. be'omer lo titgarshi bo ela bifnei beit din ploni. So
he says okay I want you to bring this גט get in
front of this בית דין beit din in this other city in
Miami and that's where the divorce will take effect. So she has
to go to Miami and then it becomes divorced. But the גמרא
Gemara says okay but he's still making her a שליח, shaliach that's
a תנאי. tnai. Why does she have to say בפני נכתב? bifnei
nechtav? So the גמרא Gemara says סוף סוף כי מטי התם איגרשה
בה sof sof ki mati hatam igrashah bah as soon as she
gets there she's divorced, so she's not a שליח shaliach and it's
not—she doesn't have to say בפני נכתב. bifnei nechtav. אלא אמר רב
הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרב אחא בריה דרב איקא Ela amar Rav
Huna bar Manoach mishmei deRav Acha brei deRav Ika דאמר לה de'amar
lah
he says to her כי מטי התם ki mati hatam when you
get there to Miami, אנחי אארעא anachi a'ara put the גט get
on the ground ושקליה veshaklei and then pick it off the ground.
So that's how you give a גט get from your right hand
to your left hand, okay? So how do you give this exact
same problem we did before, how do you—one person deliver it to
him or herself? So what you do is as a שליח shaliach
you put it on the ground, then you take off your שליח
shaliach hat, put on your wife hand hat and pick up the
גט get from the ground. The problem is that's not an act
of נתינה. netinah. You gave it to the ground, you didn't give
it to the woman. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says okay, אי
הכי הוי ליה טלי גיטך מעל גבי קרקע ei hachi havi lei
tali gittech mei'al gabei karka ואמר רבא טלי גיטך מעל גבי קרקע
לא אמר כלום. ve'amar Rava tali gittech mei'al gabei karka lo amar
klum.
If the man says to the woman, here pick up your גט
get from the ground, he didn't say anything. That it's not considered
giving it to her. He put it on the ground and she
took it from it. That's not an act of giving it to
her. So here too, she didn't give it to herself. אלא דאמר
לה Ela de'amar lah okay here's what he said: הוי שליח להולכה
עד דמטי התם hevei shaliach leholacha ad demati hatam be a שליח
shaliach for delivery till you get there to Miami and כי מטי
התם ki mati hatam when you get there הוי שליח לקבלה וקבילי
את גיטך. hevei shaliach lekabala vekabli at gittech.
Then your status will change, you'll be a שליח לקבלה. shaliach lekabala.
I mean, the רשב"א Rashba says you don't have to say you'll
be a שליח לקבלה, shaliach lekabala, you just say you'll be yourself,
but he says it was said for parallel, okay? When you get
to Miami, your status as שליח להולכה shaliach leholacha will change, you'll
become a—you'll become yourself. And then because in that act that you're
holding this גט get and all of a sudden your identity changes,
and you went from holding it as my agent to holding it
as yourself, that constitutes the act of נתינה. netinah. Okay, you got
the idea? I'm holding—I'm holding onto this גט. get I am now
the husband's agent. I'm going to say, let's say here, we'll make
it clear what the—the key moment is. When you say the word
poof, okay, you will change—you will stop being my agent and you'll
become yourself. I'm holding this גט get and I say poof. Okay,
so now I became myself. So I went from holding it as
the husband to holding it as myself. That's considered an act of
נתינה. netinah. Right?
And then because you now gave it to yourself, you have to
say בפני נכתב בפני נחתם. bifnei nechtav bifnei nechtam. עדים edim or
בית דין beit din depending on whether you need עדים edim or
a בית דין. beit din.
It's completely conceptual and in no way physical.
Correct. Correct, yes.
But that all has to be part of the husband's instruction.
That all has to be part of the husband's instruction, yes.
Maybe the origin of the phrase I'm not
myself.
Okay. All right.
So now—Rabbi, is
there a case where he can toss it into her property and
then she receives it that way? Yes.
So how is—you know that is such an excellent question and I
haven't had a chance to research that, but that's what I was
thinking. It seems to me the easiest way of solving this is
say, go to your house and throw it in your house. Right?
You don't need to be you, you just need to put it
in your property. So you be my agent and put it in
your house and then you'll divorce yourself as my agent. But I
didn't understand why the גמרא Gemara didn't say that. You know? What?
Then there's an act.
Then there's an act of giving. And you could be me and
give it to not you but give it to your property. So
I didn't understand why the גמרא Gemara didn't—didn't do that.
Placing it on the ground?
No, because on her ground there's a נתינה. netinah. On neutral ground
it wasn't given to anybody. But put into her house—Yes. Are we
anyway legally or
universally? No, but we're just trying to—'cause it's an interesting theoretical case.
How can a woman be a שליח shaliach, for herself and would
you say בפני נכתב? bifnei nechtav? Then, okay. So, someone said about
this, no this was before they had TV, we would say before
they had internet, before they had streaming video. Okay, so yes.
This is the רבנן, Rabbanan, right? We're taking it in the context.
Yeah. It's an obvious assumption that putting it on my property—no.
We're going to learn that out later. Okay. Yeah. All right. So
now—Okay. Fine. Okay, וקבילי את גיטך. vekabli at gittech. So
the
גמרא Gemara. says
okay,
so then and that act will somehow be considered an act of
נתינה. netinah. So the גמרא Gemara says והא לא חזרה שליחות אצל
בעל. veha lo hazra shelichut eitzel ba'al.
But one minute, the שליחות shelichut did not return to the husband.
So what does that mean the שליחות shelichut did not return to
the husband? So what it means is is that the way—you know
the way רש"י Rashi tells us pretty much explain it, is that
to be my שליח, shaliach, my agent, your identity has to exist
beyond the act. You have to in theory, I don't know where
the גמרא Gemara gets this idea, but you have to in theory
be able to like say, go back to the husband and say
as your agent I'm reporting that I did what you said. Is
that the way the way רש״י *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* pretty
much explain it is that to be my שליח shaliach, *shaliach*, my
agent, your identity has to exist beyond the act. You have to
in theory, I don't know where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gets this
idea, but you have to in theory be able to say go
back to the husband and say as your agent I'm reporting that
I did what you said. Now, and that means if Michael makes
me an agent to I don't know, sell David something and then
in the meantime I accept another agency there from Charlie to do
something else, that other agency doesn't compromise the fact that I'm also
Michael's agent, okay? But in this case, the only way she can
do the act is by stopping to be the husband's agent. As
while she's representing the husband, she can't also represent herself, which is
the other side of the act. So in this case, the agency
can never does cannot survive beyond the actual act itself. Okay, did
it? Yes, but not in your capacity as agent. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* again, I don't know why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
assumes that that's necessary, but it assumes that to represent that person
as an agent, it has to survive the act and be able
to survive the act itself, the agency. Okay, so therefore that doesn't
work. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* feels that that won't work. דאמר
לה *de'amar lah* fine. So here's what he said. הוי שליח להולכה
shaliach l’holacha עד דמטי התם *havay shaliach leholacha ad dematy hatam*, be
a שליח shaliach, *shaliach* for transport the גט get, *get* till you
get there, וכי מטי התם *vechi maty hatam* when you get there,
שווי שליח לקבלה shaliach l'kabala *shavey shaliach lekabala*, make appoint for yourself
a somebody to receive it for you as the wife. That's easy,
right? That's like the case we said of put it in her
house. Again, I don't know why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had to
go to, you know, to that seems to be an easy case,
put it in her house. But the גמרא Gemara... *Gemara* has something
very similar. Fine, you be my agent and you as wife appoint
somebody else to be your agent so we'll be able to give
it to that other person, okay? You'll to know who will represent
you. You'll represent me and another person will represent you and that
you know what, let's have fun. You can make me your agent
to represent you! Could do that, she would give the גט get
*get* to him. Okay, anyway fine, okay? So
what?
Right.
There you go, exactly.
Actually you could do that for קידושין *kiddushin*! She can make him
a שליח shaliach *shaliach*, oh my god that's brilliant. Okay, he can
make her a שליח shaliach *shaliach* to give the טבעת קידושין *tabaat
kiddushin* to to herself, and she can make him a שליח shaliach.
*shaliach* to accept it for herself. You get it going in the
opposite direction. Okay, we just we just solved that problem!
No, in five minutes. Okay, anyway. Alright, so that's that's...
we'd have to explain that to everybody.
What? That that actually is pretty cool. Okay, anyway. Alright, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay, אה שליח shaliach לגבי גיטין *ah shaliach legabay gitei*... so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, וכי מטי התם שווי שליח לקבלה shaliach l’kabala
*vechi maty hatam shavey shaliach lekabala*, when you get there make somebody
else your שליח shaliach *shaliach* to receive the גט get, *get*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הניחא למאן דאמר אשה עושה שליח לקבלה
מיד שליח בעל *hanicha leman de'amar isha osa shaliach lekabala miyad shaliach
baal*. That's good if a woman can make a שליח *shaliach* to
accept a גט get *get* from her husband's שליח *shaliach*. אלא למאן
דאמר אין אשה עושה שליח לקבלה מיד שליח בעל מאי איכא למימר
*ela leman de'amar ein isha osa shaliach lekabala miyad shaliach baal may
ika lemeimar*? But if a woman is not allowed to do that,
what can you say? Meaning a woman is of course allowed to
make a שליח *shaliach* to accept a גט get *get* for her,
but that is when the husband delivers the גט get, *get*. But
if it is one שליח *shaliach* with another שליח *shaliach*, there's actually
a debate, okay? So the woman can make a שליח *shaliach* to
receive a גט get. *get* directly from the husband, can she make
a גט get *get* to receive a שליח *shaliach* to make a
גט get, *get* from the husband's שליח *shaliach* is a debate. And
according to and we'll see why what it's about in a minute.
But according to the position that it's not acceptable, you don't have
an answer. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say well
let's see why it's a debate. Let's see why it's not acceptable.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says טעמא מאי *ta'ama may*, now what
is the reason according to that opinion that a woman cannot make
a שליח *shaliach* to accept a גט get *get* from her husband's
שליח *shaliach*? משום דאיכא ביזיון דבעל *mishum dika bizayon dbaal*. So one
explanation is, you know,
it's disparaging to the husband, it's embarrass- it's embarrassing to the husband.
What? I'm not good enough that you can't go ahead and accept
the גט get, *get* directly from my שליח *shaliach*? You have to
make another שליח *shaliach*? It's so funny. He appoints his wife through
a שליח *shaliach*. Oh but what, but you can't be there yourself?
I'm so offended! Okay, so that's one explanation. Now if he's giving
it himself, he can't claim being offended
because he's he's there himself and he's prepared to give it. But
if he's not there himself and it's only a שליח *shaliach*, we
don't want maybe if you want to frame it, we don't want
him to come back and say I wasn't happy with what happened,
I heard that she wasn't there herself. Okay, so if he so
if he's not present himself, then we don't want her to make
another שליח *shaliach* so he won't have a basis for complaining. Okay,
so if that's the reason, והכא בעל לא קפיד *vehacha baal lo
kapid*, here he's telling her to do this, make another שליח *shaliach*.
So there's no problem. The only reason she according to the opinion
she can't make a שליח *shaliach* for his שליח *shaliach* if he
might get upset. Here it's clear that he's not upset. Okay, that
works. Okay, אלא הניחא למאן דאמר משום ביזיון דבעל *ela hanicha leman
de'amar mishum bizayon dbaal*, that's if that's the reason. אלא למאן דאמר
משום חצירה הבא לאחר מיכן מאי איכא למימר *ela leman de'amar mishum
chatzeira haba lachar mikan may ika lemeimar*? Ah, but there's another possible
problem. The other possible problem is that it it seems too similar
to the following case. What's the following case? I take this גט
get *get* and I put it in my yard. Then I sell
this... Michael goes ahead and sells this yard to my wife. Okay,
is she divorced? No. There was no act of נתינה. netinah. If
I gave the yard directly to my wife she would be divorced,
but if it's going through Michael, it's not. So that looks now,
that is somewhat, very somewhat, structurally similar to me giving a גט
get to my שליח, my yard here is my שליח, okay, and
then my wife going ahead and appointing another שליח, she had some
interaction there with Michael which then allows that גט get, to transfer
with none of the parties directly involved. Okay, so again it's very
loosely similar. I don't really get why this is such a basis
for concern. But anyway, if that's the issue, then it has nothing
to do with the בעלת הקפדה. ba'alat hakpadah. It just looks too-
we don't like it when neither party is directly involved. It's too
much confuseable with other cases. So if that's the issue, you haven't
solved the problem because she can't make a שליח לקבלה here. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא
ומאי איכא למימר? Ella u’mai ika lemeimar? So here, so fine, try
this case. דאמרה לה הוי שליח להולכה דמטית התם D'amra lah hevei
shaliach l’holacha d’matit hatam be a שליח to deliver the גט, get
וכי מטית התם v’chi matit hatam when you get there, שוי שליח
להולכה shavei shaliach l’holacha you appoint a שליח להולכה shaliach l’holacha, in
your place, וקבליה לגיטך מיניה v’kablih l’giteich mineih and you receive the
גט get, from that person. So you don't in the end deliver
the גט get. to yourself. You deliver the גט Get, to another
שליח להולכה, shaliach l’holacha and that שליח להולכה shaliach l’holacha delivers it
to you. Which is not פשט pshat in the משנה. פשט Pshat
in the משנה is that she's actually the one delivering the גט
Get. to herself. Anyway, and there the principle is that when a
שליח להולכה shaliach l’holacha, hands over the גט Get. to another שליח
להולכה, shaliach l’holacha he has to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם b’fanai
nechtav u’v’fanai nechtam because he's the one that saw it, right? So
how do you transfer the בפני נכתב? b’fanai nechtav? The first original
one is the one who saw it. So he says בפני נכתב,
b’fanai nechtav, so the woman says בפני נכתב b’fanai nechtav to שליח
להולכה shaliach l’holacha number two and then שליח להולכה shaliach l’holacha. number
two gives the גט Get to the woman. Okay.
ואי בעית אימא V’ei ba’it eima
this caused problems somehow, this is all obviated by what? In other
words, you just say she never said any of those, right? What
did she say?
I don't know. She- too bad we accepted her testimony, like what
happens like in the first משנה בפני בית דין. b’fnei beit din.
It's a בפני בית דין, b’fnei beit din, right? Or a בית
דין? beit din?
No, no, in a בית דין. beit din. In front of a
בית דין beit din of three. All בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם b’fanai
nechtav u’v’fanai nechtam is always in front of a בית דין, beit
din, two or three. That was like the first סוגיא sugya in
the גמרא. Gemara Okay. וקבליה לגיטך מיניה. V’kablih l’giteich mineih. Now, ואי
בעית אימא, v’ei ba’it eima, if you want you could say דאמרה
ליה הוי שליח להולכה דמטית התם וכי מטית התם אמר קמי דינא
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם ומשוי בית דין שליח ולא סמינא הלך. d’amra
leh hevei shaliach l’holacha d’matit hatam v’chi matit hatam emar k’mei dina
b’fanai nechtav u’v’fanai nechtam u’mashvei beit din shaliach v’la samina helach. So
that's almost the exact same. תוספות Tosafos. says why did you need
this? This is really the same as the other point. But not
you as a private person contractor a second שליח להולכה. shaliach l’holacha
You hand over the responsibility to the בית דין beit din and
say בפני נכתב b’fanai nechtav to the בית דין beit din and
בית דין beit din will contract another שליח להולכה shaliach l’holacha to
carry it out, which by the way happens, right? Somebody is asked
to deliver a גט Get, and for whatever reason they can't. What
do they do? They have to now start looking for another שליח
in their place. So they go find a בית דין, beit din,
you give over the responsibility to the בית דין, beit din, you
go home, and בית דין beit din then will take the responsibility
of making sure that it gets delivered and then appoint another שליח.
Okay. So it's one- it's really a variation of the same type
of an answer. In case- as opposed to the case where it
sounds like a woman hands it from her right hand to her
left hand, and I like the idea of the גמרא Gemara that
just sort of says poof and then by changing her identity it's
considered an act of נתינה. The גמרא in the end has her
giving it, getting another party involved. Another party to either become her
replacement שליח להולכה or another party to be her שליח לקבלה as-
and that you have two parties here so you can do an
act of giving. Again, why the גמרא did not just have her
putting it in her property, that I don't know. Okay. הדרן עלך
המביא גט. Hadran alach hameivi get. And that is the end of
the second פרק, perek which as we see, we sort of started
with בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. b’fanai nechtav u’v’fanai nechtam. Along the way,
we dealt with issues about how the כתיבה ketivah is done, right?
That was nice. Okay. We dealt with some aspects of the חתימה
chatimah as well, and then we sort of closed the second פרק
perek with going back to בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. b’fanai nechtav u’v’fanai
nechtam. We dealt with the whole issue about a delivering a גט
Get, and a שליח to deliver a גט, Get. but who's a
good שליח to some degree also a little bit depends on בפני
נכתב b’fanai nechtav about a blind person or about- you know, about
these women who normally are not trusted to- say a woman's husband
died but with the בפני נכתב b’fanai nechtav aspect they are trusted
and so on. So it creates a nice closure of those two
פרקים. Okay. Now we go to our third פרק perek here where
we get more directly into the criteria of writing a גט Get,
and- so let's take a look. And it's so interesting because according
to רבה, Rabba, the point of בפני נכתב b’fanai nechtav was לשמה.
lishma. So this משנה in the third פרק starts with the idea
of לשמה. lishma. Okay. And again, it's a little interesting, right? We
just had a משנה that said anybody could write a גט, Get
חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh v’katan, right? We've sort of talked about
who's כשר Kasher to write a גט Get without talking about the
process of writing a גט Get and the requirements of writing a
גט, Get which this פרק deals with, which is the לשמה lishma
requirement. Okay, so let's take a look.
כל גט שנכתב שלא לשם אשה פסול. Kol get shenichtav shelo l’shem
ishah pasul. The essential part of the גט. Get? According to רבי
מאיר, Rebbe Meir, just reminding you, the writing doesn't matter, it's even
just the signing that matters. But this משנה is focusing on the
writing. Any גט get. written not for the sake of the woman
is invalid. כיצד? Keitzad? How so? היה עובר בשוק. Haya over bashuk.
You were walking in the marketplace. ושמע קול סופרים מקרין. Veshamah kol
sofrim makrin. And you heard, you passed by a scribal school, scribes.
And you heard somebody reading out the lesson. איש פלוני מגרש פלוני
ממקום פלוני. Ish ploni megaresh ploni mimakom ploni. Okay, everybody, get out
your quills, write the following
text. So-and-so divorces so-and-so from this place. Okay, and you heard that
scribal school going on. ואמר, Ve'amar, hey, זה שמי וזה שם אשתי.
zeh shmi vezeh shem ishti. Wait, that's my name, that's my wife's
name. This is a סימן מן השמים. siman min hashamayim. You know,
I was thinking about divorcing my wife. So, so, פסול. pasul, So
what? It's באשערט bashert exactly. פסול, pasul.
פסול לגרש בו. pasul legaresh bo. You can't use it because it
wasn't written for you, for your wife, for גירושין gerushin anyway. יתר
מכאן, Yeter mikan, more than this. כתב לגרש את אשתו. Katav legaresh
es ishto. Let's say I wrote it to serve as a גט,
get okay? And I was going to use it for my wife.
ונמלך. Venimlach. And I changed my mind and I threw it out.
ומצאו בן עירו. Umetzo ben iro. And then somebody in my city
who happened to have my name, whose wife was my wife's name,
they were both in the city, all the specifics were the same.
And he found it in the garbage. ואמר לו. Ve'amar lo. Oh,
and he found me actually and said to me, שמי כשמך ושם
אשתי כשם אשתך. shmi keshimcha veshem ishti keshem ishtecha. I already was
planning on divorcing my wife, and שמים, shamayim, but you know what,
you still have your גט get, available because the same names work.
פסול לגרש את אשתו. Pasul legaresh es ishto. You can't use that,
okay, either. Even though, I'm anticipating what the גמרא's going to say,
even though that was written for the real purpose, not just for
practice, but for the real purpose of using for גירושין. gerushin. Nevertheless,
it wasn't written for this man and for his wife. יתר מכאן,
Yeter mikan, more than this.
היו לו שתי נשים ושמותיהן שוין. Hayu lo shtei nashim ushmotehen shavin.
I have two wives, both with the same name, okay. כתב לגרש
את הגדולה לא יגרש בו את הקטנה. Katav legaresh es hagedolah lo
yegaresh bo es haktanah. So I wrote it to divorce my elder
wife, I can't use it for my younger. Obviously elder and younger
is immaterial. I can't use it—I wrote it for wife one, I
can't use it for wife number two. Okay, even though I wrote
it for גירושין gerushin purposes, for me, and I'm still using it
for me, but it wasn't for her, it wasn't for the wife
I'm going to use it for. Okay, יתר מכאן, Yeter mikan, more
than this. אמר ללבלר כתוב לאיזה שארצה אגרש בו. Amar lelavlar ktov
le'eizeh she'ertzeh agaresh bo. Let's say you left it open. Write the
גט, get. and say רחל בת לאה, Rachel bas Leah, both of
my wives, that's their name, and I'll decide later which one I
want to divorce. Okay, so it isn't even for the wrong woman,
it was open-ended. Maybe I should be able to determine it later,
printable like יש ברירה, yesh breira, when I make up my mind
later, it'll determine for which wife it was being written. Even that
is פסול לגרש בו. pasul legaresh bo. Okay, it has to be
for גירושין, gerushin, for this man, for this woman, all concrete, all
specific, all the time of the writing.
And the גמרא—everyone has to get her own, I can't use one
גט get, for both.
Obviously, right. So now, now the גמרא just spells out what I've
been implying as I've read the משנה. כתב לגרש את אשתו ונמלך.
Katav legaresh es ishto venimlach. ואלא רישא במאי? Ve'ela reisha b'mai? So
if the second case is that I found somebody who had a
גט get, for himself, what's the first case? That I was passing
by and people were saying this out loud. Okay, I mean I
already gave you the answer to this, but the גמרא initially thought
that that meant they were writing it for somebody else. אמר רבא
Amar Rava בסופרים העשוין להתלמד עסקינן. besofrim ha'asuyin lehitlamed askinan. No, no.
They're not writing it for somebody else. They're just practicing. It was
a סופר sofer school, they were practicing. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav
Ashi, דיקא נמי דקתני סופרים מקרין. dika nami dektani sofrim makrin. It
says you heard סופרים sofrim reading out, ולא קתני סופרים קורין, velo
katani sofrim korin, not that they were reading, but somebody was reading
to them, reciting to them, write the following. So they're in school
and they're practicing. שמע מינה. Shma mina. So that's a good דיוק.
diyuk. מאי יתר מכאן? Mai yeter mikan? Now what is the—what is
this sort of progression in the משנה? תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל: Tana
devei Rebbe Yishmael: לא זה שנכתב שלא לשם גירושין, Lo zeh shenichtav
shelo leshum gerushin, not only the one of the סופר sofer school,
who wasn't even written for a real גט, get אלא אף זה
שנכתב לשם גירושין, ela af zeh shenichtav leshum gerushin, even one that
was written to really be as a גט get for one guy,
פסול. pasul, It's invalid because it wasn't written for you. It was
his גט, get not your גט. get ולא זו שנכתב לשם גירושין
דידי, Velo zu shenichtav leshum gerushin didei, not only the one—is it
invalid, something that was written for another guy, אלא אף זה שנכתב
לשם גירושין דידי, ela af zeh shenichtav leshum gerushin didei, even one
that was written for you, but you wrote it for your other
wife, is פסול, pasul. is invalid, because you wrote it for wife
one, not for wife two. ולא זה שנכתב לשם גירושין הא, Velo
zeh shenichtav leshum gerushin ha, אלא אף זה שנכתב לשם גירושין הא,
ela af zeh shenichtav leshum gerushin ha, פסול. And not—that's a little
less clear what it means, but it means, and not only when
it was written for a specifically a different wife is it invalid,
but even when it was unspecified, it remains invalid, when it was
a type of I'll decide later, that also remains invalid. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? With some unspecified...
Right,
for some unspecified. Exactly. So מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? So מאי טעמא, Mai Ta’ama, what’s the reason that all
these things are problem? אי כתב ונתן ספר כריתות בידה, I Kasav
Venasan Sefer Kerisus Beyada, had the Torah just said deliver a
גט, get הוה אמינא למעוטי היכא דלא קא עביד לשום כריתות, Lemaiutei
Heicha Delo Ka Avid Leshum Kerisus, then the only requirement would have
been that it be written as a גט. get It can’t be
a practice. It has to be written as a גט. That’s... so
but if it’s written for a גט even for another person, it’s
a ספר כריתות. Sefer Kerisus. As long as it was legitimately written
to serve as a גט, I would have said that would have
sufficed. אבל כתב לגרש את אשתו ונמלך, Aval Kasav Lagaresh Es Ishto
Venimlach, but if somebody else wrote it, דעביד לשום כריתות, Deavid Leshum
Kerisus, it was written for a
גט, אימא כשר, Eima Kasher, maybe it wouldn’t have to be written
for me, as long as it’s written for a גט. כתב רחמנא
וכתב, Kasav Rachmana Vekasav, I have to write it. And I have
to write it is understood not necessarily I have to take quill
to parchment, but it’s understood to mean it has to be written
for me, for me as the מגרש. Megaresh. אי כתב רחמנא וכתב,
I Kasav Rachmana Vekasav, if it just said וכתב, Vekasav, הוה אמינא
למעוטי האי דלא איהו קא כתב לה. Hava Amina Lemaiutei Hai Delo
Ihu Ka Kasav Lah. That’s when it was written for another man.
Okay. אבל יש לו שתי נשים, Aval Yesh Lo Shtei Nashim, but
if I have two wives, ואיהו קא כתב לה, Veihu Ka Kasav
Lah, I’m writing it, again, not literally taking quill to paper, but
it’s being written for me as the מגרש, Megaresh, so I would
have said אימא כשר, Eima Kasher, that’s okay, it doesn’t matter which
wife it’s being written for. כתב רחמנא לה, Kasav Rachmana Lah, for
her, לשמה, Lishmah, for her sake. So it has to be for
a... for for me and for the specific wife. וסיפא למה לי,
Veseifa Lama Li, and why... what does the end teach me when
I’m leaving it open-ended? הא קמשמע לן דאין ברירה. Ha Kamashma Lan
De’ein Bereirah. You don’t get to decide later, leave it open-ended. Now,
is that a general principle of אין ברירה? Ein Bereirah? It could
be, but look at תוספות. Tosafos תוספות Tosafos says
לאיזו שארצה אגרש בו פסול. Le’eizo She’ertzeh Agaresh Bo Pasul. תוספות says
דגמרא מפרש משום דאין ברירה. Degamara Mefaresh Mishum De’ein Bereirah. ואומר רי
דאפילו מאן דסבר בעלמא יש ברירה, Ve’omer Ri De’afilu Man Desavar Be’alma
Yesh Bereirah, even if normally you could leave something open-ended, I’m separating
תרומות ומעשרות Terumos Umaysros on grain that I will identify later, or
something like that, okay? And even if that
works, הכא מודה, Hacha Modeh, here he agrees that it won’t work.
משום ד'וכתב לה' לשמה משמע שיהא מבורר בשעת כתיבה. Mishum De'vekasav Lah'
Lishmah Mashma Sheyehe Mevurar Besha'as Kesivah. Okay? It sounds like the לה
requirement is saying you can’t leave it open-ended. At the time of
the writing, it has to be clear that it’s being written for
a specific woman. So even if sometimes we allow things to be
open-ended and defined later, here we do not.
Yes. Is this the same issue we were discussing yesterday about you
could even use a template or it’s found like this? Oh, the...
so like I said a minute ago, all of this is according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that emphasizes that writing means the writing.
According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right, the וכתב Vekasav just means
וחתם. Vechasam. So as long as it’s signed with the right husband
and the right wife in mind, none of this matters. Right, so
all of this is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, right? So... and that
gets to the question of
can a חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh Vekatan write a גט, right?
So interesting, that means that this סתם משנה Stam Mishnah is רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, not רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Right, exactly. Which is
why the גמרא... well, that was a problem that the גמרא had,
that this משנה is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, but the earlier משנה
that said a חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh Vekatan can write a
גט sounded like it was רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, which led to
some interesting ways of explaining that earlier משנה.
Okay, so now let’s take a look. כתב לגרש את הגדולה לא
יגרש בו את הקטנה.
Kasav Lagaresh Es Hagedolah Lo Yagaresh Bo
Es Haketanah. So if I wrote it for wife one, I can’t
use it for wife two. If they... they both have the same
name. So the גמרא says קטנה הוא דלא מצי מגרש בה, Ketanah
Hu Delo Matzi Megaresh Bah, I can’t divorce wife number two, הגדולה
מצי מגרש בה, Hagedolah Matzi Megaresh Bah, but I can divorce wife
number one with it. Okay? But there's a problem, they both have
the same name. So is a גט that is not clear from
its own... from the words exactly who it's referring to acceptable? Okay,
that could be a case that somebody else in the town has
my name, right? And why? Because maybe if it has to testify
to what happened and it said ראובן בן יעקב Reuven Ben Yaakov
divorced רחל בת לאה, Rachel Bas Leah, okay, we have no idea.
Do you mean that ראובן בן יעקב Reuven Ben Yaakov and רחל
בת לאה Rachel Bas Leah or the other one in the city?
And maybe especially now that might have to do with if you
פסקן Pasken like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, right? If עדי חתימה כרתי,
Eidei Chasimah Karsai, as we’ve learned before, part of the גט’s identity
is that it also is a עדות Edus and testimony. So maybe
it has to be self-clear... self-very clear who it’s testifying about. Whereas
according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it could be an instrument of
divorce without being a testimony. It could be written on an erasable
background. Okay, but at least... but this is the question, is a
גט כשר Get Kasher if we don’t... it’s not self-evident who it’s
referring to? Now, part of what clarifies who it's referring to is
it's not just sounds on the ground, somebody is holding it. So
if the woman is holding it, her name is לאה בת רחל,
Leah Bas Rachel, okay, and my name is ראובן בן יעקב, Reuven
Ben Yaakov, okay, then that combined that she's holding it makes it
clear who gave it to her and who was divorced. Even if
her the co-wife has the same name, but she's the one that's
holding it.
Okay, do you add like an address?
So okay, so the גמרא speaks about adding a third generation, but
that’s not the case here. The case here was it was theoretically
usable for the other woman. So which means that it’s not self-evident
from the words in the גט who it’s referring to. Is that
a כשר גט? Okay, that’s the גמרא’s question. קטנה הוא דלא מצי
מגרש בה, Ketanah Hu Delo Matzi Megaresh Bah, you can’t use it
for the younger wife, for wife number two. הגדולה מצי למיגרש בה,
Ha-gedolah matzi me-garesh bah, you could use it for wife number one.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, זאת אומרת, zos omeres, this
teaches you, שני יוסף בן שמעון הדרים בעיר אחת, shenei Yosef ben
Shimon ha-darim be-ir achas, if you have two people with the same
name living in the city, the same city or town, הדרים בעיר
אחת, ha-darim be-ir achas, מוצין שטר חוב על אחרים. motzin shtar chov
al acherim.
They can actually take out a... what's it called? A שטר חוב,
shtar chov, a debt, an IOU
against somebody else. Here, I've got this thing that says Michael borrowed,
you know, a million dollars from ראובן בן יעקב. Reuven ben Yaakov.
I'm that ראובן יעקב. Reuven Yaakov. Right? I'm יוסף בן שמעון. Yosef
ben Shimon. So I'm taking it and saying, 'Pay me my million
dollars.' He says, 'No, I didn't borrow it from you, I borrowed
it from the other guy.' So the answer is: no, actually you're
not able to say that. Now, probably because... what's the biggest evidence
that he didn't borrow it from the other guy? I'm holding it!
Okay? So the fact that even though I'm holding it, that's enough
to say who it's talking about. It's... sure that's possible, but we're
not concerned about that. Okay? So that shows you that even though
on its own it's ambiguous who it's referring to, if the party
holding it is the relevant party, then that's okay. And that's true
here as well. Okay? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye
responded to this: אלא מעתה, Ella me-ata, רישא דקתני שמי כשמך פסול
לגרש בה. reisha de-kani shmi keshimcha pasul legareish bah. How about the
guy who said, 'I have the same name as you, let me
use this גט.' שני הוא דלא מצי למיגרש בה, Sheni hu de-lo
matzi me-garesh bah, הראשון מצי למיגרש בה. ha-rishon matzi me-garesh bah. Right?
So we have a similar case in the משנה where the man...
I can use it to divorce my wife, even though there's another
guy in the city that he's got the same name and his
wife's got the same name, right? That was the first case of
the משנה. There's another guy in the city. Okay. So now it's
a little different. Why is that a little different when the two
husbands have the same name? Because... here's the comparison the גמרא makes:
והא אמרינן דלא אחר יכול להוציא עליהם שטר חוב. ve-ha amrinan de-lo
acher yakhol lehotzi aleihem shtar chov.
Michael cannot come to me and
say, 'Look, it says יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon owes me
a million dollars, pay up.' Why can't he say that to me?
I'll say it's the other one. Now, can you say, 'Oh, but
Michael's holding it.' So what? So what you're holding it? That doesn't
prove which יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon you're talking about. When
יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon is holding it, you know which
one it's talking about. When Michael's holding it, you don't know which
one it's talking about. So the גמרא says, well, if this woman
is holding a גט and says she was divorced by יוסף בן
שמעון, Yosef ben Shimon, right? The question isn't her name. The name
in the גט, we'll assume that's the name of the person holding
it. The question is the other name in the גט. So how
come that works? You don't know which is the other one. Now
of course that's a silly question. He's married to the other one!
Right? Michael doesn't have ten proofs it's יוסף בן שמעון Yosef ben
Shimon A owes me, even if he more does business with יוסף
בן שמעון Yosef ben Shimon A rather than B, there's nothing that
shows that that's the one who he... borrowed the money from him.
But if a woman is holding it and we assume that the
person holding the גט, theirs is the name... one of the names
there, then by definition the other guy is... is her
husband. So it's a... it is a very strange challenge that אביי
Abaye makes. Once the one party's identity is determined by a גט,
the other party's identity is necessarily... well, no... okay, if the wife's
identity is determined, the husband's identity is necessarily determined. So אביי's Abaye
challenge is a funny one. So let's just read one sentence of
an answer, we'll pick up with this tomorrow. Okay? אמר והא אמרינן
ולא אחר
יכול להוציא עליהן שטר חוב?
Amar ve-ha amrinan
ve-lo acher yakhol le-hotzi aleihen shtar chov? אלא מאי אית לך למימר?
Ella mai isakh le-meimar? בעדי מסירה דרבי אליעזר היא. Be-idei mesirah de-Rabbi
Eliezer hi. הכא נמי בעדי מסירה דרבי אליעזר היא. Hakha nami be-idei
mesirah de-Rabbi Eliezer hi. Ah, no. When does it work? When does
it work if they have people that have the same name? That
there are עדי מסירה, edei mesirah, like I said before. The גט
doesn't have to testify for itself according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, a central part of the גט
is its ability to serve as עדות eidus and that the writ
testifies on its own. So for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, if people
have the same name in the town, this would be a problem.
But for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, as long as you have witnesses,
external, that are observing it being given over, then it doesn't matter
if two wives have the same name, two husbands have the same...
whatever, two men of the same name. As long as it was
written for the right person and they observed it, even if the
גט isn't testifying on its own, there's some ambiguity, it's okay because
for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the גט doesn't have to be testimony.
And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer can have that the witnesses observe it
and see it was given even if from the writ of the
גט itself it's not clear. Okay, but again, it's a very funny
why the גמרא needed to say that. Once we assume the person
holding it is the party being referred to, then that necessarily also
determines the other side of the גט as well. Okay, so it's
not clear to me why the גמרא had to say this, it
would seem it could go according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but
anyway, that's at least where אביי concludes and we'll pick up with
here with this tomorrow.
No polyandry in Judaism.